<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: spring-cloud | TOO MUCH CODING]]></title>
  <link href="http://toomuchcoding.com/blog/categories/spring-cloud/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://toomuchcoding.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-09-24T20:38:12+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://toomuchcoding.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Marcin Grzejszczak]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[blog@toomuchcoding.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Spring Cloud Contract 1.0.0.M1 Released]]></title>
    <link href="http://toomuchcoding.com/blog/2016/07/25/spring-cloud-contract-1-dot-0-0-dot-m1-released/"/>
    <updated>2016-07-25T17:07:39+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://toomuchcoding.com/blog/2016/07/25/spring-cloud-contract-1-dot-0-0-dot-m1-released</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve just published an article at the Spring blog about <a href="https://spring.io/blog/2016/07/25/spring-cloud-contract-1-0-0-m1-released">Spring Cloud Contract 1.0.0.M1 Release</a>. Check out the new project formerly known as Accurest!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Accurest becomes part of the Spring Cloud Contract]]></title>
    <link href="http://toomuchcoding.com/blog/2016/06/24/accurest-becomes-part-of-the-spring-cloud-contract/"/>
    <updated>2016-06-24T18:43:07+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://toomuchcoding.com/blog/2016/06/24/accurest-becomes-part-of-the-spring-cloud-contract</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m extremely happy to announce that we have successfully rebranded the <a href="https://codearte.github.io/accurest">Accurest project</a>. It&rsquo;s officially become part of the <a href="https://github.com/spring-cloud/spring-cloud-contract">Spring Cloud Contract</a> initiative. Ladies and Gentlemen please welcome the new projects:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://codearte.github.io/accurest/">Spring Cloud Contract Verifier</a></li>
<li><a href="https://codearte.github.io/accurest/#spring-cloud-contract-stub-runner">Spring Cloud Contract Stub Runner</a></li>
</ul>


<!-- more -->


<h2>A little bit of history</h2>

<p>Accurest was created because of lack of an easy-to-use tool for doing <a href="http://martinfowler.com/articles/consumerDrivenContracts.html">Consumer Driven Contracts</a>. From our production experience the biggest problem was lack of verification that the defined contract actually does what it says it does. We wanted to ensure that from the contract automatically tests are generated so that we can have a proof that the stubs are reliable. Since there was no such tool the first commit of Accurest took place on 12/2014. The very idea and its implementation was initially set by <a href="http://www.kubrynski.com/">Jakub Kubrynski</a> and me. The last available version of Accurest was 1.1.0 released on 06/2016 (the docs for the old version are <a href="https://codearte.github.io/accurest/deprecated/">available here</a>). During these 19 months a lot of feedback has been gathered. The tool has received a lot of very good reception and that made us want to work even harder. Many times we have decided to decrease the time required for sleeping so as to fix a bug or develop a new feature in Accurest.</p>

<h2>Notable features</h2>

<p>Speaking of features, especially quite a few of them definitely makes Accurest stand out on the &ldquo;market&rdquo; of Consumer Driven Contract (CDC) tooling. Out of many the most interesting are:</p>

<ul>
<li>Possibility to do CDC with messaging</li>
<li>Clear and easy to use, statically typed DSL</li>
<li>Possibility to copy paste your current JSON file to the contract and only edit its elements</li>
<li>Automatic generation of tests from the defined Contract</li>
<li>Stub Runner functionality - the stubs are automatically downloaded at runtime from Nexus / Artifactory</li>
<li>Spring Cloud integration - no discovery service is needed for integration tests</li>
</ul>


<p>For more information check out my posts about <a href="http://toomuchcoding.com/blog/2016/04/06/accurest-stubrunner-released/">Stub Runner</a>, <a href="http://toomuchcoding.com/blog/2016/04/30/accurest-and-stub-runner-1-dot-1-0-dot-m3/">Accurest Messaging</a> or <a href="https://codearte.github.io/accurest/">just read the docs</a>.</p>

<h2>Spring Cloud Contract</h2>

<p>In Pivotal we came to the conclusion that Accurest could become an interesting addition to our Spring Cloud tooling. Due to the increased interest of the community in the Consumer Driven Contracts approach we&rsquo;ve decided to start the <a href="https://github.com/spring-cloud/spring-cloud-contract">Spring Cloud Contract</a> initiative.</p>

<p>Accurest became <em>Spring Cloud Contract Verifier</em> (note: the name might change in the future) but for the time being will remain in the <a href="https://github.com/Codearte">Codearte repository</a>. It&rsquo;s becoming the part of Spring Cloud tooling as a mature tool with a growing community around it. Some arguments for that are that it has:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://codearte.github.io/accurest/">a nice AsciiDoc documentation that was completely rewritten following users' feedback</a></li>
<li><a href="https://gitter.im/Codearte/accurest">active Gitter channel where we try to immediately answer any support questions</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/Codearte/accurest/stargazers">Over 80 stars on Github and counting ;)</a></li>
</ul>


<p>Since we believe very much in the Consumer Driven Contract approach we also want to do the library in a Client Driven way. That means that we (server side) are very open to your feedback (consumer side) and want you be the main driver of changes in the library.</p>

<h2>Credits</h2>

<p>The Accurest project would never come to life without the hard work of the <a href="http://codearte.io">Codearte</a> developers (the order is random):</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://twitter.com/olga_maciaszek">Olga Maciaszek-Sharma</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.kubrynski.com">Jakub Kubrynski</a></li>
<li><a href="https://solidsoft.wordpress.com/">Marcin Zajaczkowski</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/mariuszs">Mariusz Smykula</a></li>
</ul>


<p>and obviously everybody who has <a href="https://github.com/Codearte/accurest/graphs/contributors">ever commited something to the project</a>.</p>

<h2>Links</h2>

<p>If you want to read more about <em>Spring Cloud Contract Verifier</em> just check out the following links.</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/Codearte/accurest">Spring Cloud Contract Verifier Github Repository</a></li>
<li><a href="http://codearte.github.io/accurest">Spring Cloud Contract Verifier Documentation</a></li>
<li><a href="http://codearte.github.io/accurest/deprecated">Accurest Legacy Documentation</a></li>
<li><a href="https://codearte.github.io/accurest/#spring-cloud-contract-stub-runner">Spring Cloud Contract Stub Runner Documentation</a></li>
<li><a href="http://codearte.github.io/accurest/#stub-runner-for-messaging">Spring Cloud Contract Stub Runner Messaging Documentation</a></li>
<li><a href="https://gitter.im/Codearte/accurest">Spring Cloud Contract Verifier Gitter</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/Codearte/accurest-maven-plugin">Spring Cloud Contract Verifier Maven Plugin</a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Zero Downtime Deployment with a Database]]></title>
    <link href="http://toomuchcoding.com/blog/2016/05/31/zero-downtime-deployment-with-a-database/"/>
    <updated>2016-05-31T11:58:52+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://toomuchcoding.com/blog/2016/05/31/zero-downtime-deployment-with-a-database</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve just published an article at the Spring blog about <a href="https://spring.io/blog/2016/05/31/zero-downtime-deployment-with-a-database">Zero Downtime Deployment with a Database</a>. So if you&rsquo;re planning on doing
zero downtime or blue/green deployment you&rsquo;d better check out that article :) The code is available here on
<a href="https://github.com/spring-cloud-samples/zero-downtime-deployment">Github</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Spring Cloud Sleuth RC1 deployed]]></title>
    <link href="http://toomuchcoding.com/blog/2016/03/25/spring-cloud-sleuth-rc1-deployed/"/>
    <updated>2016-03-25T14:18:22+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://toomuchcoding.com/blog/2016/03/25/spring-cloud-sleuth-rc1-deployed</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>On the 24.03.2016 we&rsquo;ve managed to move our <a href="https://spring.io/blog/2016/03/24/spring-cloud-brixton-rc1-is-now-available">release train called Brixton to the next station: RC1</a>.
I&rsquo;m really happy about this cause it cost us a lot of energy but it was worth it!</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m recently mostly focusing on the <a href="http://cloud.spring.io/spring-cloud-sleuth/spring-cloud-sleuth.html">Spring Cloud Sleuth project</a> and actually quite gigantic changes happened there since the M5 release. In this short post I&rsquo;ll show you the rationale and describe briefly the features related to span naming and customizations related to span propagation.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>What is Spring Cloud Sleuth?</h2>

<p>For those who don&rsquo;t know what Spring Cloud Sleuth is - it&rsquo;s a library that implements a distributed tracing solution for Spring Cloud. You can check its code at <a href="https://github.com/spring-cloud/spring-cloud-sleuth">Github</a>.</p>

<p>We&rsquo;re also trying to be aligned with the concepts, terminology and approaches present in the <a href="http://opentracing.io/">OpenTracing Project</a>.</p>

<h2>Distributed tracing terminology</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;ll quote the <a href="http://cloud.spring.io/spring-cloud-sleuth/spring-cloud-sleuth.html">documentation</a> to present some of the basic concepts of distributed tracing.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>Span</em>: The basic unit of work. For example, sending an RPC is a new span, as is sending a response to an RPC. Span’s are identified by a unique 64-bit ID for the span and another 64-bit ID for the trace the span is a part of. Spans also have other data, such as descriptions, timestamped events, key-value annotations (tags), the ID of the span that caused them, and process ID’s (normally IP address).</p>

<p>Spans are started and stopped, and they keep track of their timing information. Once you create a span, you must stop it at some point in the future.</p>

<p><em>Trace</em>: A set of spans forming a tree-like structure. For example, if you are running a distributed big-data store, a trace might be formed by a put request.</p>

<p><em>Annotation</em>: is used to record existence of an event in time. Some of the core annotations used to define the start and stop of a request are:</p>

<ul>
<li><p><em>cs</em> - Client Sent - The client has made a request. This annotation depicts the start of the span.</p></li>
<li><p><em>sr</em> - Server Received - The server side got the request and will start processing it. If one subtracts the cs timestamp from this timestamp one will receive the network latency.</p></li>
<li><p><em>ss</em> - Server Sent - Annotated upon completion of request processing (when the response got sent back to the client). If one subtracts the sr timestamp from this timestamp one will receive the time needed by the server side to process the request.</p></li>
<li><p><em>cr</em> - Client Received - Signifies the end of the span. The client has successfully received the response from the server side. If one subtracts the cs timestamp from this timestamp one will receive the whole time needed by the client to receive the response from the server.</p></li>
</ul>
</blockquote>

<p>Ok since now we&rsquo;re on the same page with the terminology let&rsquo;s see what&rsquo;s new in Sleuth.</p>

<h2>Span creation and naming</h2>

<h3>Rationale</h3>

<p>A really big problem that is there in the distributed tracing world is the issue related to naming spans. Actually that topic can be looked at from two angles.</p>

<p>First one is related to what the name of the span should look like. Should be a long and descriptive name or quite the contrary? As we write in the documentation:</p>

<blockquote><p>The name should be low cardinality (e.g. not include identifiers).</p></blockquote>

<p>Finding the name for the span is not that big of a problem from library&rsquo;s perspective. You just pass on to a span whatever the user provides. But what about the situations in which some operation is deferred in time? Or scheduled at certain intervals?</p>

<p>Second one is related to a bigger issue: for the sake of consistency of passing tracing data, should we enforce creating spans? Should we be <em>eager</em> with that or allow the user to control span creation? Cause in that way we can have a problem how to name this artificial instance.</p>

<p>For RC1 we&rsquo;ve decided that we will be eager in creating span names - but <a href="https://github.com/spring-cloud/spring-cloud-sleuth/issues/180">we will come back to the topic in the future releases</a>.</p>

<h3>Naming spans</h3>

<p>Ok so we know the why, now let&rsquo;s move to the how&hellip; There is quite a lot of instrumentation going on in Sleuth so sometimes the names of spans could sound artificial (e.g. <em>async</em> for asynchronous operations). When talking about runnables and callables often you&rsquo;re dealing with code similar to this one:</p>

<pre><code>Runnable runnable = new Runnable() {
    @Override public void run() {
        // perform logic
    }
});
Future&lt;?&gt; future = executorService.submit(runnable);
// ... some additional logic ...
future.get();
</code></pre>

<p>What the <code>Runnable</code> is an operation that you would like to wrap in a span. What should be the name of that span? How can you pass it to the <code>Tracer</code> so that the span name is set?</p>

<p>To answer those issues we&rsquo;ve introduced two approaches</p>

<ul>
<li>a <code>@SpanName</code> annotation for an explicit class that implements <code>Runnable</code> or <code>Callable</code></li>
<li><code>toString()</code> method resolution of an anonymous instance of either of those interfaces</li>
</ul>


<p>Most likely in the future releases <code>@SpanName</code> or its modification will be used more heavily to provide explicit names of spans.</p>

<p>Anyways examples could look like those in the documentation. Example for <code>@SpanName</code> annotated class:</p>

<pre><code>@SpanName("calculateTax")
class TaxCountingRunnable implements Runnable {

    @Override public void run() {
        // perform logic
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>and an anonymous instance:</p>

<pre><code>new TraceRunnable(tracer, spanNamer, new Runnable() {
    @Override public void run() {
        // perform logic
    }

    @Override public String toString() {
        return "calculateTax";
    }
});
</code></pre>

<p>Both will have the same span name. Remember that both <code>Runnables</code> should be wrapped in a <code>TraceRunnable</code> instance.</p>

<h3>Customization of span propagation</h3>

<p>It&rsquo;s pretty obvious that there&rsquo;s a lot of companies that have already created some form of distributed tracing instrumentation. In Spring Cloud Sleuth we&rsquo;re expecting the tracing headers to be containing certain names like <code>X-B3-TraceId</code> for the trace id containing headers or <code>X-B3-SpanId</code> for the span related one.</p>

<p>One of the first issues that we&rsquo;ve created was related to <a href="https://github.com/spring-cloud/spring-cloud-sleuth/issues/19">support configurable header names</a> but actually we&rsquo;ve developed it quite late. Anyways with RC1 it&rsquo;s possible to customize Sleuth in such a way that it&rsquo;s compatible with your system&rsquo;s nomenclature. Let&rsquo;s define two terms before we go any further - <code>Injector</code> and <code>Extractor</code>.</p>

<h4>Injectors</h4>

<p>In Spring Cloud Sleuth an <code>Injector</code> is actually a functional interface called <code>SpanInjector</code>. It has the following method:</p>

<pre><code>void inject(Span span, T carrier);
</code></pre>

<p>Its purpose is to take whatever is necessary from a <code>span</code> and
inject it to the <code>carrier</code>. Let&rsquo;s assume that in your system you don&rsquo;t set the headers for trace id with the name <code>X-B3-TraceId</code> but you call it <code>correlationId</code> and <code>mySpanId</code> for <code>X-B3-SpanId</code>. Then you would have to override the behavior of Sleuth by registering a custom implementation of the <code>SpanInjector</code>. Let&rsquo;s look at the following snippets from the documentation:</p>

<pre><code>class CustomHttpServletResponseSpanInjector implements SpanInjector&lt;HttpServletResponse&gt; {

    @Override
    public void inject(Span span, HttpServletResponse carrier) {
        carrier.addHeader("correlationId", Span.idToHex(span.getTraceId()));
        carrier.addHeader("mySpanId", Span.idToHex(span.getSpanId()));
        // inject the rest of Span values to the header
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>Note that this approach will work with Zipkin only if your values that you&rsquo;re passing are Zipkin-compatible. That means that the IDs are 64bit numbers.</p>

<p>Also you may wonder why do we convert values using <code>Span.idToHex</code>. We&rsquo;ve decided that we want the values of ids in the logs and in the message headers to be the very same values as the one that you can later see in Zipkin. That way you can just copy the value and put it into Zipkin to debug your system.</p>

<p>Once you have the <code>SpanInjector</code> you have to register it as a bean with <code>@Primary</code> annotation as presented below:</p>

<pre><code>@Bean
@Primary
SpanInjector&lt;HttpServletResponse&gt; customHttpServletResponseSpanInjector() {
    return new CustomHttpServletResponseSpanInjector();
}
</code></pre>

<h4>Extractors</h4>

<p>In Spring Cloud Sleuth an <code>Extractor</code> is actually a functional interface called <code>SpanExtractor</code>. It has the following method:</p>

<pre><code>Span joinTrace(T carrier);
</code></pre>

<p>Its purpose is to create a Span from the provided carrier. Let&rsquo;s have the same assumption as with the <code>SpanInjector</code> and let&rsquo;s consider a case where traceId header is named <code>correlationId</code> and spanId header is <code>mySpanId</code>. Then we customize the Spring context by providing our own implementation of the <code>SpanExtractor</code>:</p>

<pre><code>class CustomHttpServletRequestSpanExtractor implements SpanExtractor&lt;HttpServletRequest&gt; {

    @Override
    public Span joinTrace(HttpServletRequest carrier) {
        long traceId = Span.hexToId(carrier.getHeader("correlationId"));
        long spanId = Span.hexToId(carrier.getHeader("mySpanId"));
        // extract all necessary headers
        Span.SpanBuilder builder = Span.builder().traceId(traceId).spanId(spanId);
        // build rest of the Span
        return builder.build();
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>Again note that we&rsquo;re considering that the values are Zipkin compatible (64bit values for ids). Also note that we&rsquo;ve assumed that the ids are sent in a hexadecimal form like they are presented in the Zipkin UI. That&rsquo;s why we used the <code>Span.hexToId</code> method to convert it back to long again.</p>

<h2>Summary</h2>

<p>In this very short post you could see two quite big features available in the RC1 release. You can check <a href="http://cloud.spring.io/spring-cloud-sleuth/spring-cloud-sleuth.html">Spring Cloud Sleuth documentation</a> for more information about the integrations and configurations of Sleuth. Actually you can check all the things that have changed in the RC1 release by checking the <a href="https://github.com/spring-cloud/spring-cloud-sleuth/issues?q=is%3Aissue+is%3Aclosed+milestone%3A1.0.0.RC1">closed issues</a> and <a href="https://github.com/spring-cloud/spring-cloud-sleuth/pulls?q=is%3Apr+milestone%3A1.0.0.RC1+is%3Aclosed">merged PRs</a>.</p>

<p>In case of any questions do not hesitate to ping us on the <a href="https://gitter.im/spring-cloud/spring-cloud-sleuth">Gitter channel</a> or <a href="https://github.com/spring-cloud/spring-cloud-sleuth/issues">file an issue on Github</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Post on Spring blog]]></title>
    <link href="http://toomuchcoding.com/blog/2016/01/04/post-on-spring-blog/"/>
    <updated>2016-01-04T18:28:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://toomuchcoding.com/blog/2016/01/04/post-on-spring-blog</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
Hi!<br /><br />Since December I'm working for Pivotal and the Spring Cloud team. I've just posted my first blog post on the Spring blog. Check it out!<br /><br /><a href="https://spring.io/blog/2016/01/04/testing-spring-cloud-projects">Testing Spring Cloud Projects</a></div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
