<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Stubrunner | TOO MUCH CODING]]></title>
  <link href="http://toomuchcoding.com/blog/categories/stubrunner/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://toomuchcoding.com/"/>
  <updated>2017-12-03T07:15:17-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://toomuchcoding.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Marcin Grzejszczak]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[blog@toomuchcoding.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Accurest and Stub Runner 1.1.0.M3]]></title>
    <link href="http://toomuchcoding.com/blog/2016/04/30/accurest-and-stub-runner-1-dot-1-0-dot-m3/"/>
    <updated>2016-04-30T13:53:44+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://toomuchcoding.com/blog/2016/04/30/accurest-and-stub-runner-1-dot-1-0-dot-m3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Currently at the Spring Team we&rsquo;re polishing our libraries for the upcoming final release of the Brixton train. It should happen soon :) Until then I&rsquo;m spending a lot of my after work, free time on <a href="/blog/2016/04/25/accurest-docs-updated/">Accurest</a> and <a href="http://toomuchcoding.com/blog/2016/04/06/accurest-stubrunner-released/">Stub Runner</a>.</p>

<p>Today&rsquo;s post will be about the new stuff that you will be able to profit from in the upcoming <code>1.1.0</code> release of Accurest. Also you can profit from most of these features in the <code>1.1.0.M3</code> release.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ll just quickly go through the features but note that you can read about all of them in more depth in our <a href="http://codearte.github.io/accurest">documentation </a>.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Name change</h2>

<p>AccuREST started as a library used to stub HTTP calls. In the upcoming <code>1.1.0</code> release you will be able to stub messaging functionality too. That&rsquo;s why the name changes to Accurest. That&rsquo;s a fantastic name isn&rsquo;t it? ;)</p>

<p>Also since branding is important, now instead of calling <code>io.codearte.accurest.dsl.GroovyDsl</code> you can call <code>io.codearte.accurest.dsl.Accurest</code> :)</p>

<h2>Messaging support</h2>

<p>It took me quite some time to do this but it was worth it :) Several sleepless nights and now you can profit from defining contracts for messaging. In HTTP we had <code>client</code>/<code>stub</code> side and <code>server</code>/<code>test</code> side. For messaging we added methods to help discern the differences:</p>

<ul>
<li><code>publisher</code> the side for which the tests will be generated</li>
<li><code>consumer</code> the side for which the messaging endpoints will be stubbed</li>
</ul>


<h3>Contract</h3>

<p>There are 3 use cases from the message <code>Producer</code>&rsquo;s point of view.</p>

<ul>
<li>something happens in my application and I&rsquo;m producing an output message</li>
<li>someone sends a message to destination (queue/topic), I&rsquo;m listening to that message and will produce an output message somewhere else</li>
<li>someone sends a message to destination (queue/topic), I&rsquo;m listening to that message and will consume it without any message sending</li>
</ul>


<p>Here you can see examples of contracts for those three situations (you can read more about it in the  <a href="http://codearte.github.io/accurest/#messaging-top-level-elements">docs</a> ):</p>

<h4>Output triggered by a method</h4>

<p>The output message can be triggered by calling a method (e.g. a Scheduler was started and a message was sent)</p>

<pre><code class="groovy">def dsl = Accurest.make {
        // Human readable description
        description 'Some description'
        // Label by means of which the output message can be triggered
        label 'some_label'
        // input to the contract
        input {
                // the contract will be triggered by a method
                triggeredBy('bookReturnedTriggered()')
        }
        // output message of the contract
        outputMessage {
                // destination to which the output message will be sent
                sentTo('output')
                // the body of the output message
                body('''{ "bookName" : "foo" }''')
                // the headers of the output message
                headers {
                        header('BOOK-NAME', 'foo')
                }
        }
}
</code></pre>

<h4>Output triggered by a message</h4>

<p>The output message can be triggered by receiving a message.</p>

<pre><code class="groovy">def dsl = GroovyDsl.make {
        description 'Some Description'
        label 'some_label'
        // input is a message
        input {
                // the message was received from this destination
                messageFrom('input')
                // has the following body
                messageBody([
                        bookName: 'foo'
                ])
                // and the following headers
                messageHeaders {
                        header('sample', 'header')
                }
        }
        outputMessage {
                sentTo('output')
                body([
                        bookName: 'foo'
                ])
                headers {
                        header('BOOK-NAME', 'foo')
                }
        }
}
</code></pre>

<h4>No output, only input</h4>

<p>There can be only input without any output</p>

<pre><code class="groovy">def dsl = GroovyDsl.make {
        description 'Some Description'
        label 'some_label'
        // input is a message
        input {
                // the message was received from this destination
                messageFrom('input')
                // has the following body
                messageBody([
                        bookName: 'foo'
                ])
                // and the following headers
                messageHeaders {
                        header('sample', 'header')
                }
        }
}
</code></pre>

<h3>Producer side</h3>

<p>Here you can see an example of a JUnit generated test for the producer for the input / output scenario:</p>

<pre><code>// given:
 AccurestMessage inputMessage = accurestMessaging.create(
  "{\\"bookName\\":\\"foo\\"}"
, headers()
  .header("sample", "header"));

// when:
 accurestMessaging.send(inputMessage, "input");

// then:
 AccurestMessage response = accurestMessaging.receiveMessage("output");
 assertThat(response).isNotNull();
 assertThat(response.getHeader("BOOK-NAME")).isEqualTo("foo");
// and:
 DocumentContext parsedJson = JsonPath.parse(accurestObjectMapper.writeValueAsString(response.getPayload()));
 assertThatJson(parsedJson).field("bookName").isEqualTo("foo");
</code></pre>

<p>We&rsquo;re sending a message to a destination called <code>input</code>. next we&rsquo;re checking if there&rsquo;s a message at the <code>output</code> destination. If that&rsquo;s the case
we&rsquo;re checking if that message has proper headers and body.</p>

<h3>Consumer side</h3>

<p>It&rsquo;s enough to provide the dependency to proper Stub Runner module (check the next section for more information) and tell it which stubs should be downloaded. Yup, that&rsquo;s it! <a href="http://codearte.github.io/accurest/#stub-runner-for-messaging">Stub Runner will download the stubs and prepare stubbed routes</a>.</p>

<p>Sometimes you&rsquo;ll need to trigger a message somehow in your tests. That&rsquo;s why we&rsquo;ve provided the <code>StubTrigger</code> interface that you can inject! If you&rsquo;re already familiar with Stub Runner Spring then you could use the <code>StubFinder</code> bean to find the URL of your dependency. Now <code>StubFinder</code> also extends the <code>StubTrigger</code> interface thus you don&rsquo;t have to inject any additional beans in your tests.</p>

<p>There are multiple ways in which you can trigger a message:</p>

<h4>Trigger by label</h4>

<pre><code>stubFinder.trigger('return_book_1')
</code></pre>

<h4>Trigger by group and artifact ids</h4>

<pre><code>stubFinder.trigger('io.codearte.accurest.stubs:camelService', 'return_book_1')
</code></pre>

<h4>Trigger by artifact id</h4>

<pre><code>stubFinder.trigger('camelService', 'return_book_1')
</code></pre>

<h4>Trigger all messages</h4>

<pre><code>stubFinder.trigger()
</code></pre>

<h3>Integrations</h3>

<p>We provide the following out of the box integrations:</p>

<ul>
<li>Spring Integration</li>
<li>Spring Cloud Stream</li>
<li>Apache Camel</li>
</ul>


<p>Also we provide all the building blocks to provide a custom integration.</p>

<p>Just by providing the proper dependency</p>

<pre><code>// for Apache Camel
testCompile "io.codearte.accurest:accurest-messaging-camel:${accurestVersion}"
// for Spring Integration
testCompile "io.codearte.accurest:accurest-messaging-integration:${accurestVersion}"
// for Spring Cloud Stream
testCompile "io.codearte.accurest:accurest-messaging-stream:${accurestVersion}"
</code></pre>

<p>Your generated tests should just work.</p>

<h2>Stub Runner Boot</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;ve added a new module of <a href="http://codearte.github.io/accurest/#stub-runner-boot">Stub Runner</a> that operates on Spring Boot. Assuming that you&rsquo;re using Spring Cloud Stream you can create a project that has 2 dependencies:</p>

<pre><code>compile "io.codearte.accurest:stub-runner-boot:${accurestVersion}"
compile "io.codearte.accurest:stub-runner-messaging-stream:${accurestVersion}"
</code></pre>

<p>Now if you pass the proper <a href="http://codearte.github.io/accurest/#common-properties-for-junit-and-spring">Stub Runner Spring configuration</a> e.g.:</p>

<pre><code>stubrunner.stubs.ids: io.codearte.accurest.stubs:streamService
</code></pre>

<p>You will have a running app that exposes HTTP endpoints to</p>

<ul>
<li>trigger messages</li>
<li>check the URLs of the registered WireMock stubs</li>
</ul>


<h2>Accurest Maven Plugin</h2>

<p>Mariusz Smykuła has done a fantastic job by adding the <a href="http://codearte.github.io/accurest-maven-plugin/">Accurest Maven Plugin</a>. Now you can add Accurest to your project that runs with Maven. But that&rsquo;s not all since the Maven Plugin allows you to run the Accurest stubs using the <code>accurest:run</code> command!</p>

<p>Read the <a href="http://codearte.github.io/accurest-maven-plugin/">docs</a> to know more!</p>

<h2>Stub Runner changes</h2>

<h3>Messaging</h3>

<p>With messaging coming as a feature I&rsquo;ve added a bunch of messaging modules. You can read more about the <a href="http://codearte.github.io/accurest/#stub-runner-for-messaging">Stub Runner messaging modules here</a></p>

<h3>Fixed ports and versions of stubs</h3>

<p>Another feature that was missing and is really valuable is that now you can explicitly say that you want a particular dependency to be started at a given port. This feature is available since version <code>1.0.7</code> but the stub id has been changed in <code>1.1.0.M4</code> so be warned ;)</p>

<p>The ids have changed because now you can provide the desired version of the stub that you want to download.</p>

<h4>Via properties</h4>

<p>Now you can provide the id of a stub like this:</p>

<pre><code>groupId:artifactId:version:classifier:port
</code></pre>

<p>where version, classifier and port are optional.</p>

<ul>
<li>If you don’t provide the port then a random one will be picked</li>
<li>If you don’t provide the classifier then the default one will be taken.</li>
<li>If you don’t provide the version then the + will be passed and the latest one will be downloaded</li>
</ul>


<p>Where port means the port of the WireMock server.</p>

<p>So if you provide your dependency like this:</p>

<pre><code>stubrunner.stubs.ids: io.codearte.accurest.stubs:streamService:0.0.1-SNAPSHOT:stubs:9090,io.codearte.accurest.stubs:anotherService:+:9095
</code></pre>

<p>It will make Stub Runner:</p>

<ul>
<li>download a stub with groupId: <code>io.codearte.accurest.stubs</code>, artifactId: <code>streamService</code>, version: <code>0.0.1-SNAPSHOT</code>, classifier: <code>stubs</code> and register it at port 9090</li>
<li>download a stub with groupId: <code>io.codearte.accurest.stubs</code>, artifactId: <code>anotherService</code>, latest version, default classifier (<code>stubs</code>) and register it at port 9095</li>
</ul>


<h4>Via fluent API</h4>

<p>When using the AccurestRule you can add a stub to download and then pass the port for the last downloaded stub.</p>

<pre><code>@ClassRule public static AccurestRule rule = new AccurestRule()
                .repoRoot(repoRoot())
                .downloadStub("io.codearte.accurest.stubs", "loanIssuance")
                .withPort(12345)
                .downloadStub("io.codearte.accurest.stubs:fraudDetectionServer:12346");
</code></pre>

<p>You can see that for this example the following test is valid:</p>

<pre><code>then(rule.findStubUrl("loanIssuance")).isEqualTo(URI.create("http://localhost:12345").toURL());
then(rule.findStubUrl("fraudDetectionServer")).isEqualTo(URI.create("http://localhost:12346").toURL());
</code></pre>

<h2>Technical changes</h2>

<p>Apart from features we&rsquo;ve done some technical refactoring.</p>

<h3>Grape -> Aether</h3>

<p>I&rsquo;ve migrated the mechanism used to download dependencies from Groovy Grape to Aether. We had a lot of issues with Grape and Aether works very well for now. That&rsquo;s a backwards incompatible change so if you had some custom Grape configuration then you&rsquo;ll have to port it to Aether.</p>

<h3>Dependencies fixed</h3>

<p>We had some problems with explicit and transitive dependencies that got fixed. The Accurest jars should be smaller.</p>

<h3>Summary</h3>

<ul>
<li>A lot work was done around Accurest and CDC</li>
<li>Quite soon we&rsquo;ll release the 1.1.0 version</li>
<li>You can use stubs of your dependencies that communicate over messaging</li>
<li>You can use fixed ports and versions for your dependencies</li>
<li>If you like the project star it on <a href="https://github.com/Codearte/accurest">Github</a> :) That will give us additional boost of energy to spend on coding instead of sleeping ;)</li>
</ul>


<h3>Links</h3>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/Codearte/accurest">Accurest Github Repository</a></li>
<li><a href="http://codearte.github.io/accurest">Accurest Documentation</a></li>
<li><a href="http://codearte.github.io/accurest/#stub-runner">Stub Runner Documentation</a></li>
<li><a href="http://codearte.github.io/accurest/#stub-runner-for-messaging">Stub Runner Messaging Documentation</a></li>
<li><a href="https://gitter.im/Codearte/accurest">Accurest Gitter</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/Codearte/accurest-maven-plugin">Accurest Maven Plugin</a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Accurest Docs Updated]]></title>
    <link href="http://toomuchcoding.com/blog/2016/04/25/accurest-docs-updated/"/>
    <updated>2016-04-25T21:49:59+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://toomuchcoding.com/blog/2016/04/25/accurest-docs-updated</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After a lot of sleepless nights I&rsquo;ve finally migrated the <a href="http://codearte.github.io/accurest/">Accurest Docs</a> from Github&rsquo;s Wiki to Asciidoctor.
With that change the vast majority of our snippets is taken from the tests. Also thanks to that change it will be much easier to keep the docs up to date
since the documentation lives together with the code.</p>

<p>Quite frankly recently when I didn&rsquo;t code <a href="https://github.com/spring-cloud/spring-cloud-sleuth">Spring Cloud Sleuth</a> I did a lot around <a href="http://codearte.github.io/accurest/">Accurest</a> and messaging so stay tuned! For sure there will be a new post about Consumer Driven Contracts and Messaging.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[AccuREST Stub Runner Released]]></title>
    <link href="http://toomuchcoding.com/blog/2016/04/06/accurest-stubrunner-released/"/>
    <updated>2016-04-06T11:05:58+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://toomuchcoding.com/blog/2016/04/06/accurest-stubrunner-released</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It&rsquo;s been a good release time recently! I&rsquo;m blogging here at <a href="http://toomuchcoding.com">Too Much Coding blog</a> more about releases then about any concrete topics ;)</p>

<p>After releasing <a href="/blog/2016/03/25/spring-cloud-sleuth-rc1-deployed/">Spring Cloud Sleuth as a part of Brixton RC1</a> we have just released a version 1.0.4 of <a href="https://github.com/Codearte/accurest">AccuREST</a>. We&rsquo;ve fixed a couple
of bugs but we&rsquo;ve introduced a couple of big features including:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/Codearte/accurest-maven-plugin">Maven plugin support</a></li>
<li><em>Stub Runner</em> functionality</li>
</ul>


<p>This post will describe the latter feature in more depth.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Introduction</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;ve given quite a few talks about the library called <a href="https://github.com/4finance/micro-infra-spring">Micro-Infra-Spring</a> where I presented how you can profit from the <em>Stub Runner</em> functionality. Since my leaving the company owning that repository, the project is almost not maintained at all. For quite a long time any development was done mostly by me and actually I was the author of most of the <em>Stub Runner&rsquo;s</em> code. Due to the aforementioned and the fact that <em>Stub Runner</em> is tightly coupled with AccuREST&rsquo;s stub generation feature I&rsquo;ve decided to migrate it to the AccuREST&rsquo;s repository.</p>

<h2>AccuREST recap</h2>

<p><em>Stub Runner</em> is tightly coupled with the concepts coming from AccuREST. For more information about AccuREST you can check my <a href="/blog/categories/accurest/">blog entries</a> or check <a href="https://github.com/Codearte/accurest">AccuREST project on Github</a>. If you don&rsquo;t have a clue what that is I&rsquo;ll try to do a very fast recap.</p>

<p>AccuREST is a <a href="http://martinfowler.com/articles/consumerDrivenContracts.html">Consumer Driven Contracts</a> verifier in which you define the contract of your API via a Groovy DSL. From that DSL, on the server side, tests are created to check if your contract is telling the truth. From the <em>Stub Runner&rsquo;s</em> perspective more interesting is the client side. For the client side AccuREST generates WireMock stubs from the provided DSL so that the clients of that API can be provided with reliable stubs.</p>

<h2>What is Stub Runner?</h2>

<p>Now that we remember what AccuREST does we can take a look in more depth at <em>Stub Runner</em>. Let&rsquo;s assume that we have a following flow of services (btw. <a href="http://cloud.spring.io/spring-cloud-sleuth/spring-cloud-sleuth.html">this is a screenshot from Zipkin integrated with Spring Cloud Sleuth</a> )</p>

<p><img src="/images/accurest/stubrunner/dependencies_accurest.png" alt="Dependencies" /></p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s imagine ourselves as developers of the <em>service2</em> - the one that calls <em>service3</em> and <em>service4</em>. Since we&rsquo;re doing the CDC (<a href="http://martinfowler.com/articles/consumerDrivenContracts.html">Consumer Driven Contracts</a>) approach let&rsquo;s assume that the stubs of <em>service3</em> and <em>service4</em> got already deployed to some Maven repository.</p>

<p>If I&rsquo;m writing integration tests of <em>service2</em> I&rsquo;ll for sure have some points of interaction with <em>service3</em> and <em>service4</em>. Most likely in the majority of cases I&rsquo;ll just mock those interactions in my code but it would be valuable to have a real HTTP call done to the other application. Of course I don&rsquo;t want to download both services and run them only for integration tests - that would be an overkill. That&rsquo;s why the most preferable solution at this point would be to run the stubs of my collaborators.</p>

<p>Since I&rsquo;m too lazy to do things manually I&rsquo;d prefer the stubs to be automatically downloaded for me, the WireMock servers started and fed with the stub definitions.</p>

<p>And that&rsquo;s exactly what <em>Stub Runner</em> can do for you!</p>

<h2>How does it work?</h2>

<h3>Concept</h3>

<p><a href="https://github.com/Codearte/accurest/wiki/8.-Stub-Runner">Stub Runner</a> at its core is using Groovy&rsquo;s Grape mechanism to download the stubs from a given Maven repository. Next it unpacks them to a temporary folder. Let&rsquo;s assume that you have the following structure of your WireMock stubs inside the stub JAR (example for a <code>service3-stubs.jar</code>)</p>

<pre><code>├── META-INF
│   └── MANIFEST.MF
└── mappings
    └── service3
        ├── shouldMarkClientAsFraud.json
        ├── notAWireMockMapping.json
        └── shouldSayHello.json
</code></pre>

<p><em>Stub Runner</em> will scan the whole unpacked JAR for any <code>.json</code> files. There is a convention that stub definitions are placed under the <code>mappings</code> folder. So it will pick <code>shouldMarkClientAsFraud.json</code>, <code>notAWireMockMapping.json</code> and <code>shouldSayHello.json</code> files.</p>

<p>Next, a WireMock instance is started for each dependency and every found JSON is attempted to be parsed as a WireMock stub definition. Any exceptions at this point are ignored (so assuming that <code>notAWireMockMapping.json</code> is not a valid WireMock definition, the exception will be suppressed). In our scenario 2 WireMock servers will be started - one for <code>service3</code> and one for <code>service4</code>.</p>

<p>That way you don&rsquo;t have to copy the stubs manually. The stubs are centralized since they are stored in a Maven repository. It&rsquo;s extremely important cause <em>Stub Runner</em> downloads always the newest version of the stubs so you can be sure that your tests will break the moment someone does an incompatible change.</p>

<h3>API</h3>

<p>From the developer&rsquo;s perspective there are only a handful of <em>Stub Runner&rsquo;s</em> classes that should be used. In the majority of cases you will use the following ones:</p>

<h4>StubFinder</h4>

<p>An interface that allows you to find the URL of the started WireMock instance. You can find that URL by
passing the Ivy notation (<code>groupId:artifactId</code>) or just the <code>artifactId</code> - <em>Stub Runner</em> will try to take care of the rest.</p>

<pre><code class="groovy">interface StubFinder {
  /**
   * For the given groupId and artifactId tries to find the matching
   * URL of the running stub.
   *
   * @param groupId - might be null. In that case a search only via artifactId takes place
   * @return URL of a running stub or null if not found
   */
  URL findStubUrl(String groupId, String artifactId)

  /**
   * For the given Ivy notation {@code groupId:artifactId} tries to find the matching
   * URL of the running stub. You can also pass only {@code artifactId}.
   *
   * @param ivyNotation - Ivy representation of the Maven artifact
   * @return URL of a running stub or null if not found
   */
  URL findStubUrl(String ivyNotation)

  /**
   * Returns all running stubs
   */
  RunningStubs findAllRunningStubs()
}
</code></pre>

<h4>RunningStubs</h4>

<p>A structure representing the already running stubs. Give you some helper methods to retrieve Ivy representation of a particular stub, find a port for a stub etc.</p>

<p><img src="/images/accurest/stubrunner/running_stubs.png" alt="RunningStubs" /></p>

<h4>StubRunning</h4>

<p>A contract for classes that can run the stubs:</p>

<pre><code class="groovy">interface StubRunning extends Closeable, StubFinder {
  /**
   * Runs the stubs and returns the {@link RunningStubs}
   */
  RunningStubs runStubs()

}
</code></pre>

<h4>StubRunner</h4>

<p>Represents a single instance of ready-to-run stubs. It can run the stubs and will return the running instance of WireMock wrapped in <code>RunningStubs</code> class. Since it&rsquo;s implementing <code>StubFinder</code> can also be queried if the current groupid and artifactid are matching the corresponding running stub.</p>

<h4>BatchStubRunner</h4>

<p>If you have multiple services for which you want to run the WireMocks with stubs it&rsquo;s enough to use <code>BatchStubRunner</code>. It iterates over the given <code>Iterable</code> of <code>StubRunner</code> and executes the logic on each of them.</p>

<h2>Running Stub Runner</h2>

<p>In all the examples below let&rsquo;s assume that the stubs are stored in the Maven repository available under <code>http://toomuchcoding.com</code> URL. As <em>service2</em> I&rsquo;d like to download the stubs of <code>com.toomuchcoding:service3</code> and
<code>com.toomuchcoding:service4</code> services.</p>

<h3>Stub Runner as a fat JAR</h3>

<h4>How to use it?</h4>

<p><em>Stub Runner</em> comes with a main class (<code>io.codearte.accurest.stubrunner.StubRunnerMain</code>) which you can run with the following options:</p>

<pre><code> -maxp (--maxPort) N            : Maximum port value to be assigned to the
                                  Wiremock instance. Defaults to 15000
                                  (default: 15000)
 -minp (--minPort) N            : Minimal port value to be assigned to the
                                  Wiremock instance. Defaults to 10000
                                  (default: 10000)
 -s (--stubs) VAL               : Comma separated list of Ivy representation of
                                  jars with stubs. Eg. groupid:artifactid1,group
                                  id2:artifactid2:classifier
 -sr (--stubRepositoryRoot) VAL : Location of a Jar containing server where you
                                  keep your stubs (e.g. http://nexus.net/content
                                  /repositories/repository)
 -ss (--stubsSuffix) VAL        : Suffix for the jar containing stubs (e.g.
                                  'stubs' if the stub jar would have a 'stubs'
                                  classifier for stubs: foobar-stubs ).
                                  Defaults to 'stubs' (default: stubs)
 -wo (--workOffline)            : Switch to work offline. Defaults to 'false'
                                  (default: false)
</code></pre>

<p>You can run that main class from IDE or build yourself a fat JAR. To do that just call the following command:</p>

<pre><code>./gradlew stub-runner-root:stub-runner:shadowJar -PfatJar
</code></pre>

<p>Then inside the <code>build/lib</code> there will be a fat JAR with classifier <code>fatJar</code> waiting for you to execute.</p>

<p>Coming back to our example once the fat JAR is built I would just call the following command the retrieve the stubs of <em>service3</em> and <em>service4</em> from the Maven repository available at <code>http://toomuchcoding.com</code>.</p>

<pre><code>java -jar stub-runner-1.0.4-SNAPSHOT-fatJar.jar -sr http://toomuchcoding.com -s com.toomuchcoding:service3:stubs,com.toomuchcoding.service4
</code></pre>

<h4>When to use it?</h4>

<p>Running <em>Stub Runner</em> as a main class makes most sense when you&rsquo;re running some fast smoke tests on a deployed application where you don&rsquo;t want to download and run all the collaborators of that application. For more rationale behind such an approach you can check my article about <a href="/blog/2015/09/27/microservice-deployment/">Microservice Deployment</a></p>

<h3>Stub Runner JUnit Rule</h3>

<h4>How to use it?</h4>

<p>You can use the <em>Stub Runner&rsquo;s</em> JUnit rule to automatically download and run the stubs during your tests. The <code>AccurestRule</code> implements the <code>StubFinder</code> interface thus you can easily find the URLs of the services that you&rsquo;re interested in.</p>

<p>This is how you could do it with Spock:</p>

<pre><code class="groovy">class SomeSpec extends Specification {

  @ClassRule @Shared AccurestRule rule = new AccurestRule()
      .repoRoot('http://toomuchcoding.com')
      .downloadStub("com.toomuchcoding", "service3")
      .downloadStub("com.toomuchcoding:service4")

  def 'should do something useful when service3 is called'() {
        given:
            URL service3Url = rule.findStubUrl('com.toomuchcoding', 'service3')
        expect:
            somethingUseful(service3Url)
    }

  def 'should do something even more useful when service4 is called'() {
        given:
            URL service4Url = rule.findStubUrl('service4')
        expect:
            somethingMoreUseful(service4Url)
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>or with plain Java JUnit:</p>

<pre><code>public class SomeTest {

  @ClassRule public static AccurestRule rule = new AccurestRule()
      .repoRoot("http://toomuchcoding.com")
      .downloadStub("com.toomuchcoding", "service3")
      .downloadStub("com.toomuchcoding:service4");

  @Test
  public void should_do_something_useful_when_service3_is_called() {
        URL service3Url = rule.findStubUrl("com.toomuchcoding", "service3");

        somethingUseful(service3Url);
  }

  @Test
  public void should_do_something_even_more_useful_when_service4_is_called() {
        URL service4Url = rule.findStubUrl("service4");

        somethingMoreUseful(service4Url);
  }
}
</code></pre>

<h4>When to use it?</h4>

<p>You can use this rule in any place you want to if we don&rsquo;t provide any integration with an existing framework.</p>

<h3>Stub Runner Spring</h3>

<h4>How to use it?</h4>

<p>You can use the <em>Stub Runner&rsquo;s</em> Spring configuration to download the stubs of your collaborators and run the WireMock server upon Spring context booting. We&rsquo;re providing the <code>StubRunnerConfiguration</code> that you can import in your tests. In that configuration we&rsquo;re registering a <code>StubFinder</code> bean that you can autowire in your tests.</p>

<p>Having the following <code>application.yaml</code> file:</p>

<pre><code class="yml">stubrunner.stubs.repository.root: http://toomuchcoding.com
stubrunner.stubs.ids: com.toomuchcoding:service3:stubs,com.toomuchcoding.service4
</code></pre>

<p>This is how you could do it with Spock</p>

<pre><code class="groovy">@ContextConfiguration(classes = Config, loader = SpringApplicationContextLoader)
class StubRunnerConfigurationSpec extends Specification {

  @Autowired StubFinder stubFinder

  def 'should do something useful when service3 is called'() {
      given:
          URL service3Url = stubFinder.findStubUrl('com.toomuchcoding', 'service3')
      expect:
          somethingUseful(service3Url)
  }

  def 'should do something even more useful when service4 is called'() {
      given:
          URL service4Url = stubFinder.findStubUrl('service4')
      expect:
          somethingMoreUseful(service4Url)
  }

  @Configuration
  @Import(StubRunnerConfiguration)
  @EnableAutoConfiguration
  static class Config {}

}
</code></pre>

<h4>When to use it?</h4>

<p>In your tests if you have Spring and don&rsquo;t have Spring Cloud. Also you can add it in compile time (of course you would have to add some Spring profiles so as not to run it on production) to profit from a &ldquo;developer&rdquo; mode of running microservices. That means that if you boot up your application to click around it - all the stubs around you would have already been downloaded and started.</p>

<h3>Stub Runner Spring Cloud</h3>

<h4>How to use it?</h4>

<p>You can use the <em>Stub Runner&rsquo;s</em> Spring Cloud configuration to profit from the stubbed collaborators when using Spring Cloud&rsquo;s abstractions over service discovery and when you&rsquo;re using Netflix Ribbon. <em>Stub Runner Spring Cloud</em> configuration is an <code>AutoConfiguration</code> so it&rsquo;s automatically started for you.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s assume that you&rsquo;re referring to <em>service3</em> as <code>service3</code> in your code and to <em>service4</em> as <code>shouldMapThisNameToService4</code>. That means that you&rsquo;re using for example the <code>@LoadBalanced</code> <code>RestTemplate</code> in the following way (don&rsquo;t use field injection as I do in this example!!):</p>

<pre><code class="groovy">@Component
class SomeClass {

  @Autowired @LoadBalanced RestTemplate restTemplate

  void doSth() {
    // code...
    String service3Response = restTemplate.getForObject('http://service3/name', String)
    String service4Response = restTemplate.getForObject('http://shouldMapThisNameToService4/name', String)
    // more code...
  }

}
</code></pre>

<p>If the service Id that you&rsquo;re using to call other services maps exactly to the name of the artifact Id in a Maven repository then you&rsquo;re lucky and don&rsquo;t have to do anything to find your running stubs. If however that&rsquo;s not the case - don&rsquo;t worry, you&rsquo;ll just have to map it yourself.</p>

<p>The <code>stubrunner.stubs.idsToServiceIds</code> property is the root path to a map in which the <em>key</em> is the <em>artifactID</em> of the downloaded stub and the <em>value</em> is the <em>serviceId</em> used in the code.</p>

<p>Having the following <code>application.yaml</code> file:</p>

<pre><code class="yml">stubrunner.stubs.repository.root: http://toomuchcoding.com
stubrunner.stubs.ids: com.toomuchcoding:service3:stubs,com.toomuchcoding.service4

stubrunner.stubs.idsToServiceIds:
  service4: shouldMapThisNameToService4
</code></pre>

<p>This is how you could do it with Spock</p>

<pre><code class="groovy">@ContextConfiguration(classes = Config, loader = SpringApplicationContextLoader)
class StubRunnerConfigurationSpec extends Specification {

  @Autowired SomeClass someClass

  def 'should not explode'() {
      when:
          someClass.doSth()
      expect:
          noExceptionThrown()
  }

  @Configuration
  @EnableAutoConfiguration
  static class Config {}

}
</code></pre>

<h4>When to use it?</h4>

<p>When you&rsquo;re using Spring Cloud. You can profit from <code>Stub Runner Spring Cloud</code> also in &ldquo;developer&rdquo; mode as presented in the <code>Stub Runner Spring</code> section.</p>

<h3>Additional Configuration Options</h3>

<p>You can set the default value of the Maven repository by means of a system property:</p>

<pre><code>-Dstubrunner.stubs.repository.root=http://your.maven.repo.com
</code></pre>

<p>The list of configurable properties contains:</p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th> Name </th>
<th> Default value </th>
<th> Description </th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td> stubrunner.port.range.min </td>
<td> 10000 </td>
<td> Minimal value of a port for a WireMock server </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> stubrunner.port.range.max </td>
<td> 15000 </td>
<td> Maximum value of a port for a WireMock server </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> stubrunner.stubs.repository.root </td>
<td>  </td>
<td> Address to your M2 repo (will point to local M2 repo if none is provided) </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> stubrunner.stubs.classifier </td>
<td> stubs </td>
<td> Default classifier for the JARs containing stubs </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> stubrunner.work-offline </td>
<td> false </td>
<td> Should try to connect to any repo to download stubs (useful if there&rsquo;s no internet) </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> stubrunner.stubs </td>
<td> </td>
<td> Default comma separated list of stubs to download </td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<h2>Summary</h2>

<p><em>Stub Runner</em>:</p>

<ul>
<li>Has already proven to be a very useful tool when doing CDC.</li>
<li>Was battle tested and more companies are declaring their interest in using it.</li>
<li>Helps you produce an API that should make both sides (server and the client) equally happy (or unhappy but still they&rsquo;re both equal in their emotions ;) ).</li>
<li>Is language / technology agnostic - you can run it as a fat JAR, use it with Spring, Guice or whatever you want.</li>
<li>Helps you speed up the feedback cycle both from the API design and the compatibility perspective.</li>
</ul>


<h2>Links</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/Codearte/accurest">AccuREST Github Repository</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/Codearte/accurest/wiki/8.-Stub-Runner">Stub Runner WIKI</a></li>
<li><a href="https://gitter.im/Codearte/accurest">AccuREST Gitter</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/Codearte/accurest-maven-plugin">AccuREST Maven Plugin</a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
